A Guide to the Blackall William Ball Collection, 1782-1784, 1802
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Blackall William Ball Collection 1782-1784, 1802
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 2005.14
18 items.
Ball, Blackall William, 1761-1812
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2005
Biographical/Historical Information
Blackall William Ball was born in Dublin, Ireland, but soon moved with his parents to the backcountry of Pennsylvania. At the age of fifteen, he was commissioned as an Ensign in the 12th Pennsylvania Regiment in 1776. Seeing action at the battles of Princeton, Brandywine, and Germantown in 1777, he was promoted to the rank of First Lieutenant and transferred to the 3rd Pennsylvania by the end of 1778. In the summer of 1781, Lieutenant Ball found himself progressing southward with the amalgamated Pennsylvania Continental Line from New Jersey, arriving at "the college of Williamsburg" on September 4th, and on to Yorktown in support of the allied siege.
Scope and Content
Collection comprises 6 journals with a series of observations on the march from York, PA under General Anthony Wayne through the south to the Yorktown campaign, a military commission, portrait print of the author, 10 issues of contemporary newspapers with news of the Yorktown campaign.
Arrangement
18 items.
Index Terms
Persons:
Ball, Blackall William, 1761-1812
Geographical Names:
Virginia-History-Revolution, 1775-1783; Pennsylvania-History-Revolution, 1775-1783; Yorktown (Va.)-History-Siege, 1781; United States-History-Revolution, 1775-1783
Collection Contents:
- Papers
  - Photograph made from painting (Box 1)
  - Diary
    - June 3-September 3, 1781
    - September 29-November 5, 1781
    - September 3, 1781-January 4, 1782
    - January 4-April 17, 1782
  - Orderly book, November 27, 1783-February15, 1784
  - Journal, 1802
  - Commission, February23, 1784
  - Newspapers
    - Salem Gazette, November 29, 1781
    - The Continental Journal and Weekly Advertiser, October 18, 1781
    - The Connecticut Gazette; and the Universal Intelligencer, October 5-November 30, 1781 (8 issues)